# 你这招有点新鲜
This is new.
# 跟三叔不一样吧 用熟米熏
It's different from San Shu's method, we use cooked rice instead.
# 烟熏的鱼吧
Smoked fish?
# 烟鱼
Yes, smoked fish.
# 洗好的鱼我就先切一字刀（双面）
We will make parallel slices first (both sides).
# 这样便于入味
This will help the fish to absorb flavor.
# 然后最后咱们打一个十字口
Finally, we will slice a cross on the fish.
# 这就行了
Like this.
# 放到盆里边
And put the fish into a bowl.
# 我们现在跟着切点料
Now, we will chop some other ingredients.
# 这是二伯常用的手法
This is what Er Bai would normally do.
# 葱头
Shallots.
# 这样腌完了以后这东西又去腥味
Marinating with shallots will remove the fishy taste.
# 而且淡淡的蔬菜香味才能融进去
The fish will also absorb the vegetable's flavor,
# 这样其实吃出东西来更加健康
which is very healthy.
# 这腌多久呢
How long should we marinate it?
# 我们要使的盐少点
Since we can't add to much salt.
# 我们腌个两个小时 半天都可以
we can marinate it for two hours, or even half a day.
# 如果说我要不等着吃
However, if you are not in a hurry of eating this dish,
# 我搁一宿也没问题是吧
you can leave it overnight.
# 时间长了它更容易入味
The longer you marinate, the more flavor it will absorb.
# 基本的料就差不多了
This is pretty much all the ingredient we will use.
# 您这用料够狠的
Er Bai, you are using a lot of ingredients.
# 这点料比这鱼都快贵了
All those ingredients add up to be even more expensive than the fish.
# 但是我觉得您追求完美
But, I think you are pursuing for perfection.
# 其实我们热爱生活
Yes, enjoying our life,
# 好好的善待自己善待家人
treating ourselves and our families well,
# 其实是一件不错的事
is a really good thing.
# 放的什么啊这
What is this?
# 这个是沙姜粉
This is sand ginger powder.
# 如果说需要的时候
This is not necessary, however.
# 我是让它味道更丰富一些
I am just adding it to create a richer flavor.
# 实际上我在家里边
Honestly, for home-cooking,
# 就用盐花椒腌就行了
we can just use Sichuan peppercorns and salt.
# 这个是盐
This is salt.
# 这盐好像不一样啊
It looks different from normal salt.
# 就是淮盐
It is Huai Salt (salt mixed with spices)
# 用盐就使劲搓 把味道搓进去
We will massage the fish with salt, in order to infuse all the flavors in.
# 这个五香粉来一点
We will add some five-spices powder.
# 让它味道更浓一点
To make it more fragrant.
# 最后来点柱侯酱就行了
Lastly, we will add some Chu Hou paste.
# 柱候酱 黄酒
Chu Hou paste, huangjiu (yellow rice wine).
# 这个味道非常好
This flavor is so good.
# 而且柱侯酱的味道非常浓郁
Especially the Chu Hou paste.
# 融到一块非常香 就完了
It mixed so well with the other ingredients.
# 我就腌上它
We will leave it
# 我们腌它半天就可以了
marinate for half a day.
# 我怕耽误大家时间
Since we don't want to waste your time,
# 这是提前腌好的
we have prepared a marinated fish.
# 腌好了味儿了
Fully marinated.
# 用手稍微捋捋它 给它弄干净了
Use our hands to clean it up.
# 这样就行了
Like this.
# 然后拿个东西先可以蒸了
Now, we can steam it.
# 水开了 咱就直接蒸上了
After the water starts to boil, we can steam the fish.
# 底下弄点底油要不然它粘啊
We need to brush some oil on the bottom to prevent it from sticking.
# （垫筷子）让它把鱼撑起来
We can use chopsticks to hold the fish up.
# 能成熟的更好 蒸多长时间
So it can cook thoroughly. For how long?
# 八分钟到十分钟
Eight to ten minutes.
# 我这个熏法你看见没有再介绍介绍
Have you seen this smoking method? I'll explain it.
# 桂皮 甘草 大料
Cinnamon, licorice, star anise.
# 这甘蔗你看 切碎了
This is sugarcane, we chopped it.
# 然后就是白糖了
And then is sugar.
# 就行了很简单
This is simple.
# 这个没什么复杂的
Nothing complicated.
# 咱这就等着熟了就开始开熏
Now we will just wait for fish to finish steaming, then we can start smoking it.
# 你看就这种方法刚才腌制这种方法
As for the marination,
# 如果说我们要不愿意熏
if you don't like to smoke it,
# 刷上冰糖老抽 刷一点颜色
you can brush it with sugar and dark soy sauce to create some color,
# 撒上芝麻进烤箱 直接焗去了
sprinkle some seasame seeds, and throw it into the oven.
# 按照你师父的说法就是一通百通
Using your master's words, master the one to master all.
# 我们说我爱吃鸡我把鸡做熟了
We can also cook chicken, or duck
# 一熏鸡 熏鸭子
to make smoked chicken or smoked duck.
# 熏什么都可以 熏鸽了
You can smoke anything with my recipe, even smoked pigeon.
# 你通了 全通了
You master one, you then master all.
# 基本时间到了 你看看怎么样
It's time, what do you think?
# 你看这鱼很香
Smells really nice.
# 然后我们加料
Now we can put in the ingredients for smoking.
# 锡纸 再搁一层
Two layers of aluminum foil at the bottom.
# 这是米饭 大米饭
This is rice.
# 你这招有点新鲜啊 跟三叔不一样吧
This is new. It's different from San Shu's method.
# 用熟米熏 你看见没有
We use cooked rice instead.
# 其实这些都是过去老的手艺
This is an old recipe.
# 有的用熟米 有的用生米
Some use cooked rice; some use raw rice.
# 熟米熏是什么原理
What's the purpose of using cooked rice?
# 它水汽足 更容易释放米的香味
They have lots of steam, which is easier to release the fragrance of the rice.
# 还不容易糊
It can also prevent burning.
# 你看
See?
# 甘蔗 米饭 二伯用的是熟饭
Sugarcane and rice. Er Bai is using cooked rice.
# 这也是我第一次看到的
This is the first time I ever see it.
# 硬点都没事 就是家里的剩米饭就行
We can use any type of cooked rice. Overnight rice works fine.
# 白糖 其实（糖）应该是在底下的
I should have layered the sugar at the very bottom.
# 容易会出这种焦糖的味道是吧
In order to create a caramel flavor, right?
# 搅拌均匀
Mix them well.
# 这糖就铺到底下去了是吧
Now the sugar gets to the bottom.
# 桂皮 大料两片 然后甘草
Cinnamon, two star anises, and some licorice.
# 二伯这方法跟三叔截然不同
Er Bai's method is completely different from San Shu's.
# 这就可以了
It should be good now.
# 好下锅啦 抹了点油（防粘）
Ok, let's put the fish in (brush some oil to prevent sticking).
# 点火 等烟冒起来咱就关上盖
Turn up the fire. Close lid when we see smoke coming out.
# 二伯这个方法跟三叔天壤之别
This is just a new world compare to San Shu's method.
# 完全不一样
Completely different.
# 这烟快起来了
The smoking is comming out.
# 起来就赶紧盖上 大火
Close the lid quickly and turn up the fire.
# 我的熏跟您的还不一样
My way of smoking is also different from yours.
# 所以说我就弄不懂
So I was quite confused at first.
# 看上色了吗
Is the fish getting its color?
# 还不行 火还是不够旺
Not enough. The fire is not high enough.
# 您这是颠覆了一个熏的方法
You just created an entirely new way of smoking food.
# 我又学到了一个新的熏法
And I learned it today!
# 你知道为什么吗
You know why?
# 不能跟三叔一样
I must be different from San Shu.
# 我跟大爷不是一个师父
Me and Da Ye also have different masters.
# 学的流派的东西不一样
So we learned different cooking styles.
# 这东西它没有什么定规矩
However, cooking doesn't have rules.
# 我现在还原的是什么
What I am doing now,
# 我还原的就是一个过去一程序
is just to bring back an old recipe,
# 我一点都没改的东西就这么做的
with nothing changed.
# 过去生熏为什么叫生熏呢
Why did people call it "raw smoke" in the past?
# 就不蒸这鱼的时候
Because you only smoke the fish,
# 熏就能把它熏熟了
without steaming it.
# 二伯这一蒸我懵了
I was really confused when Er Bai started to steam the fish.
# 另外它腌的时候没有上色 没有酱油
In addition, we didn't add any soysauce when marinating.
# 但你要鸡鸭不能上色
However, when you are making chicken or duck, don't add soysauce.
# 我把这鸡鸭卤完了
If you stew them first,
# 用酱汤卤完再熏 变黑了
then smoke. Then turn black.
# 套路不一样
Different methods.
# 可以啦 不能再熏啦
Okay, the fish is done.
# 那我就关火 关小火焖它一下
Should I turn off the fire? Put it on low heat first.
# 二伯小火多长时间
For how long, Er Bai?
# 小火咱开完以后在家里边
For home-cooking, three to four minutes on low heat.
# 也就三分钟四分钟 再关两分钟
Then, turn off the stove and leave it inside for two minutes.
# 关两分钟焖一下的目的是
The purpose of leaving it inside is that
# 把烟都焖进去
the smoke will all get into the fish.
# 火要在加热的时候气是往上走的
When heating, the steam and smoke are traveling up.
# 一关火它这气流往下返
After turning the fire down, they start to fall down.
# 烟熏的味就往下 全糊在鱼上了
And thus all the smoke flavor will get down into the fish.
# 所以要有一个沉淀的过程
So it is like a precipitation process.
# 三分钟好了 现在关火
Three minutes in. Now turn off the fire.
# 二伯关火了啊
Er Bai, I'm turning off the fire.
# 再闷两分钟是吧
Then leave it for two minutes?
# （颜色）上来了啊 正合适
The color is perfect.
# 这颜色上来了吧 这个颜色真好
The color is so nice.
# 走 好极了
Good.
# 你看你这饭到现在还不行
However, the rice is still not done yet.
# 你知道为什么我这饭多了
You know what, I think I added too much rice.
# 你看这样你看看
See?
# 这有什么好处
The benefit of this
# 你看没事（不粘锅）
is that it won't stick.
# 你先尝 谢谢大爷
You try it first. Thank you, Da Ye.
# 你看我们是一家人
We are a family now.
# 这个味道回味非常悠长
The aftertaste is very fragrant.
# 熏味香味很足
The smoked flavor is also very nice.
# 它搁熟米 它熟熏
Because it uses cooked rice,
# 它时间那么长但是它不会糊
it won't burn no matter how long you smoke.
# 三叔这种东西需要什么
As for San Shu's method,
# 真的需要是掌握火候的高超
you really need to control the fire perfectly.
# 火力的大小 控制太难
This is hard to control.
# 我这个你不用控制
However, my method solves this problem.
# 只要你慢慢熏 只要时间到了
If you just smoke the right amount of time,
# 看看颜色是吧 你就能熏出美味来
you can create deliciousness.
# 还有一个什么 刚才用大爷的说
And as Da Ye just mentioned,
# 如果说嫌（上）颜色慢 你们在腌制的时候
if you like darker color,
# 我们可以加点酱油
you can add some soysauce when marinating.
# 如果是中途颜色不够
If you have already started smoking but isn't satisfied with the color,
# 我们可以把时间加长点x
we can lengthen the smoking time
# 你熏个十分钟十五分钟都没事
to ten or even fifteen minutes.
# 其实我觉得最关键的还有一个
Actually, I think the key is that
# 不是说熏的颜色有多重为好
no matter what the color looks like,
# 只要我们是烟熏
if our smoking
# 有烟熏的香味
has the smoking flavor,
# 就好了 好
it is then good! Yes!
# import ending.sbv 0:07:25.100